Guide to the Baker Collection of Wire Recordings ARS.0069
Archive of Recorded Sound
Baker Collection of Wire Recordings
1940-1964
ARS.0069
Baker, Michael H.
1 box: 37 spools of wire recordings
Archive of Recorded Sound
37 off-air recordings, primarily of the New York Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra in the 1950s.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Baker Collection of Wire Recordings was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Zachary Baker in 2005.
Scope and Contents
Wire recordings, primarily of classical performances from the 1950s, given to the archive by Zachary Baker, Judaica Hebraica Curator at Stanford University Libraries. The collection belonged to his father, Michael H. Baker. Presumably recorded off the radio by Mr. Baker, these wire recordings capture works by Beethoven, Brahms, Mozart, Bartok, Wagner, Verdi, Haydn and others, performed almost entirely by the New York Philharmonic under the batons of Guido Cantelli, Bruno Walter, Arturo Toscanini, and Dmitri Mitropoulos. Soloists include Jascha Heifetz, Robert Cassadesus, Artur Rubinstein, and Gregor Piatigorsky. There are also three non-music recordings; the one regarding the Rosenberg case is a dub from a transcription of a radio play titled "They Must Not Die", produced by the San Francisco Labor Theatre for the Bay Area Committee to Save the Rosenbergs circa 1952 or 1953. Notations on the boxes are indistinct, with some erasure. Spelling has been corrected when known (many are spelled phonetically, as if jotted down from the radio). Different recordings of the same performances are known to have been released commercially, but none in the collection appear to be copies of published releases.
Indexing Terms
Baker, Zachary M.
- 1. La Nos; Rake's Progress / Stravinsky; [aria tylo?] (Box 1)
- 2. Beethoven 6th; Toscanini; Heifetz; [Siegfried?] (Box 1)
- 3. Beethoven; Toscanini; Heifetz (Box 1)
- 4. Brahms Concerto; Toscanini; Horowitz (Box 1)
- 5. Brahms; Toscanini; Schumann; [Piatigorsky?]; Atwater Kent Finals, 1949 (Box 1)
- 6. Brahms Concerto; Heifetz; Schumann cello (Box 1)
- 7. [Boris?] (Box 1)
- 8. Mozart Concerto 21, C major; Gieseking; Cantelli; N.Y. Philharmonic, 1955-03-05 (Box 1)
- 9. Yuri Suhl, author who wrote in Yiddish and English (Box 1)
  Suhl, Yuri, 1908-1986
- 10. The Rosenberg Case ["They Must Not Die" radio drama] (Box 1)
- 11. Brahms Double Concerto; Stern; Rose; Bruno Walter; N.Y. Philharmonic, 1954-11-28 (Box 1)
- 12. Orson (Box 1)
- 13. Verdi Requiem, Cantelli; N.Y. Philharmonic; Tucker; Turner; Hines, 1955-02-05 (Box 1)
- 14. Mozart Concerto C; N.Y. Philharmonic; [Cassadesus] (Box 1)
- 15.Toscanini; Orpheus [Gluck Orfeo], 1952-11-22 (Box 1)
- 16. Pennario; Bartok Concerto; Liszt Mephisto; Oistreich; Mozart Concerto no. 5; N.Y. Philharmonic; Mitropoulos (Box 1)
- 17. Wagner; Flagstad; Bruno Walter; N.Y. Philharmonic Farewell Program, 1952-03-23 (Box 1)
- 18. [Talo?]; Mitropoulos; N.Y. Philharmonic; [Frachisiotti?] (Box 1)
- 19. Wagner; Toscanini, 1953-03-08 (Box 1)
- 20. Brahms II; N.Y. Philharmonic; Mitropoulos; Cassadesus, 1952-04-07 (Box 1)
- 21. Mozart Requiem; Bruno Walter; N.Y. Philharmonic (Box 1)
- 22. Brahms German Requiem; Bruno Walter; London Siegfried, 1954 (Box 1)
- 23. Tchaikovsky Trio in A Minor. Heifetz; Piatigorsky; Rubinstein (Box 1)
- 24. Beethoven Missa Solemnis in D, Op. 123; Toscanini; [Nan Merriman, mezzo-soprano Eugene Conley, tenor], 1953-03-28 (Box 1)
- 25. Mozart; Saint-Saëns; Mitropoulos, N.Y. Philharmonic; Cassadesus, 1955-11-13 (Box 1)
- 26. Mozart Concerto D 45; Serkin (Box 1)
- 27. Brahms; [Toscanini?] (Box 1)
- 28. Heifetz; [Haydn?] (Box 1)
- 29. Beethoven Concerto No. 3; Cantelli, N.Y. Philharmonic; Firkusny, 1955-03-12 (Box 1)
- 30. Brahms Symphony no. 2; Haydn; Bruno Walter; N.Y. Philharmonic Rehearsal, 1954-11 (Box 1)
- 31. Brahms; Boccharini, Piatigorsky; Heifetz (Box 1)
- 32. Trio; Heifetz; Piatigorsky; Rubinstein; [Bach?] (Box 1)
- 33. Beethoven Violin Sonata No.1, No.3 (not no.2); Heifetz; Emanuel Bay (Box 1)
- 34. [Verdi] Otello; Sutherland (Box 1)
- 35. Pennario; Gabor; Sanford; [Schumann?] Quartet (Box 1)
- 36. Tchaikovsky To a Poet; Heifetz, Piatigorsky; Rubinstein (Box 1)
- 37. Rosa Raisa interview, NBC radio (press release included), 1964-03-04 (Box 1)
- 38. Brahms concerto (empty box) (Box 1)